Guide to the Law Dames records, 1951-1973 UA.31.13.0004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Law Dames records
1951-1973
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. School of Law. Law Dames
UA.31.13.0004
2.5 Linear Feet
The Duke Law Dames was a social and service organization composed of law student wives, women law students, and wives of the law school faculty and alumni. Collection consists of reports, meeting minutes, constitutions and by-laws, newsletters, flyers, calendars of events, various printed material and scrapbooks.
about 1,500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Duke Law Dames records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1974.
Historical Note
The Duke Law Dames was a social and service organization whose objective was to promote fellowship and to assist members in obtaining all benefits from the Duke-Durham area. Membership was open to law student wives, women law students, and wives of the law school faculty and alumni, although, the composition consisted mainly of law student wives. The organization presented an opportunity for wives to talk over their "common interests, enjoy interesting and educational programming, and most importantly to have fun." The group sponsored lectures, cooking demonstrations, fashion shows, holiday parties, and other assorted social and educational events. Structurally the Law Dames consisted of a president, vice president, secretary, and treasurer. In addition, there were chairs of programming, social events, publicity, and special projects. Officers were elected on an annual basis.
Collection Overview
Contains material pertaining to the operations and activities of the Duke Law Dames with the inclusive dates 1951-1973. Materials present include reports, minutes of general meetings and the executive council, correspondence and memoranda, newsletters, flyers, manuals, and assorted printed material including cookbooks composed by the Dames and a welcome guide for wives of Duke Law students. Also present are material accumulated by several organization presidents including officer's reports, minutes of the executive council, newsletter drafts, officer election material, and various printed material. There are also three scrapbooks that contain clippings documenting various social events sponsored by the Dames and also letters, officer lists and member rosters, flyers, event calendars, newsletters, photographs, and other assorted ephemera.
Related Material
School of Law Reference Collection, 1934-1999
University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Women law students -- North Carolina -- Durham; Lawyer’s spouses -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University. School of Law; Law Dames; Duke University. School of Law -- Faculty; Duke University. School of Law. Law Dames
- General Files, 1951-1973 and undated, 1 box
  Scope and Contents note
  Series contains general material accumulated by various Law Dame members and includes announcements and memos concerning events, special groups, and the election of officers. Newsletters, constitution and by-laws, reports, material pertaining to similar national and regional organizations such as the National Law Wives, and printed material are also present. Printed material includes a cookbook composed by the Dames, "Culinary Casebook," and a welcome manual for wives of Duke Law students.
  - Annual reports, president, 1955-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1951, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, 1955-1956, 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - "Culinary Casebook," 1972 (Box 1)
  - "Culinary Casebook," undated (Box 1)
  - Elections, 1971, undated (Box 1)
  - Favorite Recipes, 1966, undated (Box 1)
  - Groups and events, 1966-1967, 1971, undated (Box 1)
  - "Introducing Duke Law School," 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meetings, 1954, 1969-1971, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1966, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Member manuals, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Members and officers, 1955-1959, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
  - National Lawyer's Wives, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Newsletter, 1969-1972 (Box 1)
  - Officer's reports, 1961-1962, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Printed material, 1961-1962, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Procedure sheets, flyers, council meetings, 1969 April-1970 April (Box 1)
- President's Files, 1964-1973, 1 box
  Series contains material accumulated by various Law Dames presidents with inclusive dates 1964-1973. Material includes officer reports, executive council minutes, officer election material, newsletter drafts, member rosters, and assorted printed material. Series is arranged chronologically.
  - General, 1964-1969, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Memoranda, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Officer's reports, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - President's report, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Meetings, programs, newsletters, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Officer's reports, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Executive Council meetings, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Fliers, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Officer's reports, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks, 1959-1973, 1 box
  Series consists of three scrapbooks that contain clippings documenting the Dames in the news: lectures, meetings of special groups, various social and community events, and events involving Duke University and Law School faculty. There are also flyers, letters, event calendars, newsletters, photographs, and other assorted ephemera. Series arranged chronologically with inclusive dates 1959-1973.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1959-1969 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1969-1972 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 3, 1972-1973 (Box 3)